בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is ק"ל א', Kuf Lamed
Aleph, 131. We pick up on the bottom of ק"ל עמוד ב'.
Kuf Lamed Amud Bet. We pick up with... I'm sorry, תא שמע
tashma מניין. minayin. The word מניין minayin is eight lines from the
bottom or seven lines from the bottom. We are still dealing with
רב חסדא Rav Chisda's statement that if somebody damages the gifts that
are going to a כהן, kohein,
specifically the focus was on זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zeroa lechayayim vekeiva, but
it also referred to more classic gifts like תרומה ומעשר, truma umayser,
or we actually made a comparison to the gifts that are going
to the poor, like לקט שכחה ופאה. leket shikcha upeah. If you
damage these or eat them, destroy them, you cannot... you don't have
to pay in court because there's nobody who can file suit. ממון
שאין לו תובעין Mamon she'ein lo tovin because it's owned by the
collective of the כהנים kohanim or the collective of the poor. That
is in contrast to another explanation which is even more radical, which
suggests that they don't own it at all until you give it
to them based on the verse of... what do you call it...
of וזה. vezeh. And that you have a מצווה mitzvah to give
it to them but they don't own it to them. But because
the גמרא Gemara is going beyond the זרוע לחיים וקיבה zeroa lechayayim
vekeiva and comparing it to many different categories,
תרומה, truma, מעשר, mayser, gifts to the poor, the גמרא Gemara is
really focusing more on the explanation that there is nobody to file
suit. ממון שאין לו תובעין, Mamon she'ein lo tovin, it's owned by
the collective. And therefore the last thing the גמרא Gemara said is
that there is a concept of מידת חסידות, midat chasidut, maybe more
than a מידת חסידות, midat chasidut, because you still owe the collective
the money even though they can't file suit. So if you're doing
the right thing, you should reimburse, you know, give it to the
poor if it was money of the poor, give it to the
כהנים kohanim in tzar, but there's no way that you can be
brought to court. Yes, sorry.
So this would mean that if this argument is accepted, that there's
no such thing as a class action lawsuit?
Well, basically. That is correct. Although this is a little bit different
than class action because class action means a thousand people were injured,
each one of them individually, and they're all combining their suits. Whereas
this is nobody in particular was injured. Right? So one person כהן
kohein wouldn't have got... didn't get it. One poor person didn't get
it. We don't know which one. So that is very... that's different
than the classic class action lawsuit. I don't know if there's an
analogue to that in secular law, but here somebody in this group
lost out, but not... you can't prove that it was any particular
person. Okay, so that's actually what this case is. Rava, what if
in מילואים miluim so
you would know how many people... how many כהנים kohanim were in
that particular day, time, whatever?
That would be by קרבנות, korbanot, by who you're giving your תרומה
truma to or who you're giving your זרוע לחיים וקיבה zeroa lechayayim
vekeiva to, it could be anybody in the world. So you don't
know who's who and what. Exactly. Exactly. There is a discussion in
גיטין Gittin if you traditionally gave it to one person, if that
person has more standing. Let's continue. Now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: תא שמע, Tashma, מניין לבעל הבית שאכל פירותיו טבלים, minayin leba'al
habayit she'achal peirotav tevalim, how do you know if the homeowner, the
person with the, you know, with all of the grain that he's
supposed to now give the gift to the כהנים kohanim and לויים,
levi'im, how do you know if he ate his food, his grain
and his fruit, with the טבל, tevel, without having separated תרומות ומעשרות?
trumot uma'asrot? וכן לוי שאכל מעשרותיו טבלים, Vechein levi she'achal ma'asrotav tevalim,
or a לוי, levi, even after you give the לוי levi מעשר,
ma'aser, he has to give תרומת מעשר, trumat ma'aser, a tenth of
that to the כהנים. kohanim. What if he ate his מעשר ma'aser
without separating it out? Now, when you do one of those things,
it's actually a pretty serious thing. It's חייב מיתה בידי שמים, chayav
mita bidei shamayim, okay? It's a very weighty sin to eat those
טבל. tevel. But now we're going... we're not focusing on the sin
part of it, we're talking about the civil liability part of it.
So you ate your מעשר ma'aser without taking תרומה, truma, you ate
all of your fruit without taking תרומה, truma, do you have to
reimburse the כהן kohein or the לוי levi that lost out as
a result? But you never actually separated off your תרומה ומעשר truma
uma'aser when you ate it. So how do you know... yes?
You have to give it in the same time?
What do you mean the same time?
Because the לוי levi and the כהן... kohein... if you're...
yeah, if you've taken in like a whole, you know, grain and
you've harvested grain, you give a little bit to the כהן kohein
which is תרומה, truma, and then you give a tenth to the
לוי levi which is מעשר, ma'aser, and then another tenth even which
you're going to eat in ירושלים Yerushalayim which is מעשר שני ma'aser
sheni or to the עניים. ani'im. So yeah, it's all part of
the same process. Okay?
And you could give to any לוי? levi?
Yeah, any לוי levi or any כהן. kohein. So now you had
to... so that's the point. Who's going to collect? So you went
ahead and you ate it without taking off תרומות ומעשרות. trumot uma'asrot.
מניין שפטור מן התשלומין? Minayin shepatur min hatashlumin?
How do you know you're exempt from payment? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar,
the verse says: ולא יחללו את קדשי בני ישראל, Velo yechalelu et
kodshei benei Yisrael, you shall not desecrate the sanctified things, the holy
things of the children of Israel, אשר ירימו לה', asher yarimu l'Hashem,
that they will separate off, raise off to God. אין לך בהן
אלא משעת הרמה ואילך. Ein lecha bahen ela mishe'at harama va'eilach.
You, the כהנים, kohanim, only have a right to them or the
לויים levi'im from the time they are separated off. So the verse
says 'which will be separated off', so it's saying they're not yours
until they're separated off. Yes, the person has an obligation to separate
them from the grain, but there's no sense of your ownership of
them, you the כהן kohein or the לוי, levi, your ownership of
them until they actually are separated off. So the גמרא Gemara makes
the very obvious imp... The גמרא Gemara says הא משעת הרמה ואילך,
Ha mishas harama v'eilach,
that's only because it's still טבל, tevel, but as soon as you
separate off the תרומה ומעשר, terumah u'ma'aser, מי המשלם, mi hamishalem, it
sounds like they do fully own the תרומה ומעשר terumah u'ma'aser as
soon as they've been designated and separated off and that if you
were to eat it, you would have to pay, right? That's a
pretty good proof. It sounds like you only don't pay because it's
not yet been separated. But once you actually have תרומה ומעשר, terumah
u'ma'aser, if you ate it, you'd have to pay. Pretty good proof.
Even if you hadn't separated?
No, he, this says if you didn't separate it, you don't pay.
So the point inference is, but as soon as you separated it,
if you were to eat it then, you would pay, right? So
the גמרא Gemara says אמאי, amai, why is that? להוי כמזיק מתנות
כהונה או אוכלן, lehavei kemazik matnot kehuna o ochelan, let that be
exactly רב חסדא's Rav Chisda case, you damaged or ate the gifts
of כהונה. kehuna. So the גמרא Gemara gives a very unusual, you
know, narrow אוקימתא, ukimta, that אוקימתא ukimta is like, you know, limiting
it to a very particular case. What are we talking about? דאתו
לידיה בטבליהו. de'asu liyadei bitveila hu.
We're talking about, what we're contrasting it to is not that when
it's טבל tevel and you ate it, you don't pay, i.e. and
therefore the inference is when you have separated it off, you do
pay. No, we're contrasting it to if it's טבל tevel but the
כהן kohen has already received it and then you were to damage
it, you would pay. So what we're contrasting is not being טבל
tevel versus non-טבל, tevel, we're contrasting טבל tevel in your hands versus
טבל tevel in the כהן's kohen hands. When it's in your hands
and it's טבל tevel and you damage it, you don't pay, but
as soon as you gave it to the כהן, kohen, even if
you gave it to the כהן kohen in the טבל tevel state,
then he entitled, he owns the תרומה terumah that's there and if
you were to damage it, you would have to pay him. One
minute, דקסבר האי תנא, d'kasavar hai tanna, and this תנא Tanna is
of the opinion מתנות שלא הורמו כמי שהורמו דמיין, matnot shelo hurmu
kemi shehurmu damyan, that even before it's been separated, it's like it
has been separated. Now again, this is going entirely against the grain
and the thrust of this משנה mishna or ברייתא, braita, whatever it
is,
because the whole point here is that there's no status until it's
been separated. The whole point is to draw the line between before
it's been separated and after it's been separated and it doesn't matter
whose hands it's in. And the גמרא Gemara completely reverses the teaching
of the ברייתא. braita. No, no, it doesn't matter if it's been
separated or not. That's like the תרומה's terumah already there. What matters
is, is it in your possession? Then you don't have to pay
yet as opposed to when you've given it to the כהן, kohen,
then you do have to pay even if it's still תרומה. terumah.
So תוספות Tosafot is very bothered with this and he tries to
explain why the גמרא Gemara went in this direction. But this is
a classic case where you have somebody who makes a statement, רב
חסדא Rav Chisda says you don't have to pay, you have evidence
against it, and the גמרא Gemara will try ways of framing it
narrowly or sometimes in an unusual way in order to say that
it's not an absolute contradiction. But this ברייתא braita certainly seems to
strongly say that yes, once you've separated it, then it doesn't matter
whose possession it's in. But the גמרא Gemara reverses it to say
it doesn't matter if you've separated it, it matters whose possession it's
in. Yes.
How are you going to damage it after you've already given it
to the כהן? kohen?
You sneak into his house and you damage it. It would be
a very, very unusual case, right? Or you gave it to the
כהן kohen and then you said, "Wait, I want it back!" and
you try grabbing it back and in the process it got destroyed.
You know, you'd have to create some strange scenario. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara now says תא שמע, Ta shema, let's try again.
It's on its way. Right.
But if it's on its way, then it would be a question
when it's considered yet whether the כהן kohen owns it. תא שמע,
Ta shema, come in here.
הרי שאנסו בית המלך גרנו, Harei she'anso beit hamelech gorno,
so let's say the king, you know, has basically now seized your
property for taxes, back taxes. Okay, so and they've taken all of
your grain, which has in it, you know, which you would have
otherwise given תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot from this grain, but they've taken,
you know, ten boxes of grain for back taxes. Now, had they
not taken it, one of those boxes would have gone to a
לוי Levi for מעשר ma'aser and a smaller amount would have gone
to a כהן kohen for תרומה. terumah. Okay, so but they've taken
these ten boxes away. Do you still have to give a box
of grain to a לוי Levi for מעשר? ma'aser? What's the story?
So let's see what it says. אם בחובו, Im bechovo, if this
was a real debt like you really owed taxes, then חייב לעשר,
chayav le'aser, you have to give מעשר ma'aser from some other grain
and give it to the לוי Levi because he got cheated out
of one box of מעשר ma'aser and basically, you know, you really
owed that money so you benefited from the grain that would have
been his מעשר. ma'aser. But אם באנפרות, im be'anparut, there's a question
here what the גירסא girsa is, אנפרות, anparut, אגרפות, agrafot, but basically
it means that the property is being seized unjustly. Like the king
is coming in and just taking your property because he wants it,
but you don't really owe those taxes. So if it's some type
of forceful seizure, then פטור מלעשר, patur mile'aser, then you really didn't
use this to get exempt yourself from a debt. So since you
didn't use it to exempt yourself from a debt, it was just
stolen from you, then you don't have to make good to the
לוי. Levi. Okay, but it's like reminds me of that joke that
two guys are on a subway and somebody comes in and says,
"Okay, everybody hand me all your money." So he says, "Oh, John,
here's that twenty dollars I owe you." So...
So if it's being stolen from you, right, then you didn't, anyway,
I don't know why, anyway, bit somewhat similar. Anyway, if it's being
stolen from you, you didn't get out of a debt that way,
so you don't have to pay the לוי Levi back from the
money that was stolen from you. But if you were really paying
a debt, then you used essentially money that would have been his,
one of those boxes would have gone to him, and therefore you
have to give it to him. So this certainly seems to be
like a case of מזיק מתנות כהונה, mazik matnot kehuna, he doesn't
have it yet, it got destroyed, it was your fault, it got
taken, it was your fault, you have to pay him back. So
isn't that a proof that there's a sense of paying back and
obligation even before it's been given? Yes, Charlie.
So to the one this implies that a king is probably not
exempt from giving the tithes like any other Israel.
Oh, this not that the king has to pay. This is that
you are you've had your property seized by the king. Okay, so
if because of your property was seized, those ten boxes, that was
a real debt that you had, right, so you have to make
good of one of those boxes to the לוי. Levi.
So what if the king is himself a כהן, kohen, which happens
חשמונאים Hashmonaim times?
All right,
let's not go there right now. All right, anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says, so you see, so you see why do you have
to pay even though the לוי Levi hadn't taken possession of it?
Don't you see that there's a debt that's accrued? So the גמרא
Gemara says שאני התם דקמשתרשי ליה. shani hatam dekamishtarshe leh. There it's
different because you basically literally like you take it takes root by
him. Now what does that mean? This is an important concept that
the גמרא Gemara has sometimes, which is obligations that are incurred not
through a formal process but through a reality of having benefited from
somebody else's property. Let me give you an example of that. An
example is, let's say the גמרא Gemara says my sheep falls off
of a roof and hits onto your grain and its fall is
cushioned as a result of hitting onto your grain. Now in terms
of damages, I don't have to pay you because let's say it
happened in a רשות הרבים reshut harabim and therefore I don't pay
for those types of damages in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, but the
end result was that my sheep I've now derived benefit from your
property. Okay, so even though there was no formal thing, like I
didn't do an act of damage, I didn't do borrowing money, but
I actually as it were conceptually have some of your property by
me because because of your property I have some bottom line benefit
in my bank account in my sheep. Or if my sheep ate
your food, even though I don't have to pay damages if it
ate in the public domain, but the reality is is that my
sheep now saved itself from a meal and I saved myself from
giving my sheep meal, so I have some benefit in my sort
of ledger that accrued from your property even though there was no
formal act that obligated that obligates payment. That's an idea that's in
the גמרא Gemara about like דקמהני ליה dekaheneh leh that you derive
benefit and sometimes the phrase is used משתרשי ליה. mishtarshe leh. It's
taken root in your property. You basically have some benefit that's taken
root by you and therefore it's only right that you give that
benefit back to the person from whom you've received it. Okay, so
that's the concept here. The concept here is if I damage the
לוי's Levi property before any particular לוי Levi owned it, when it
was owned by the collective, the ממון השבט, mamon hashevet, so I
didn't damage anything that was owned by a particular person, nobody can
take me to court, I'm exempt. But when in this case it
was used to pay off a debt, I actually have some benefit
by me. I've received ten dollars, one box worth of benefit from
the collective of the כהנים. kohanim. So same way if your ball
rolled into my yard I would have to give you back your
ball, right, so let's say for example here's an analogy, let's say
a ball owned by the רבים rabbim rolled into my yard. So
even if nobody can take me to court, I'm not supposed to
leave that ball in my yard, I have to find some way
to give it back to the community. So therefore this benefit now
took root by me that I got one box worth of benefit
by paying my debt off with it, so therefore I have to
now give it back to the לויים. Levi'im. But רש"י Rashi says
this is not the case of רב חסדא Rav Chisda because רב
חסדא's Rav Chisda point is it can't be demanded in court. And
here also nobody is saying it can be demanded in court. And
here but here because there is some benefit by you you have
to make good. Now the question that תוספות Tosafot asks, which is
the obvious question is, is that I understand the contrast of that
to damaging מתנות כהונה, matnot kehuna, damaging there's no benefit, but remember
רב חסדא Rav Chisda also said if I ate מתנות כהונה, matnot
kehuna, so if I had this מעשר ma'aser by me and I
ate it, רב חסדא Rav Chisda says I don't have to do
anything. Well says תוספות Tosafot how is eating it different than paying
off your debt, right? In both ways you've got some bottom line
benefit, why don't you have to give that benefit back? And תוספות
Tosafot says there is a
difference because eating you could have gone without a meal. So the
sense that you really have something more a positive on your ledger
as a result is not so obvious by the fact that I
just ate. There's no... have some bottom line that I now have
extra value, you know, in my account. But the fact that I
paid off a debt, and I only had to use nine bucks
of my own to pay off the debt when it was a
ten buck debt, and one of those bucks was מעשר, maaser, I
really have some bottom line benefit in my bank account. And that
heightened sense of benefit, that means that I have to give it
back. So yes, I can't be demanded in court. I'm not really—there's
not a particular person I damaged, but that abstract sense of having
received benefit demands that that benefit somehow be given back to the—to
the collective of the כהנים. kohanim. That's this principle, very important halakhic
principle of משתרשי ליה. mishtarshi leh. Some say it's rabbinic, but whatever—it's
rabbinic or biblical, conceptually it's very important. תא שמע, Ta shema, come
and hear. אמרו
לו, Amru lo, they said—they said to a—a person said to the
butcher, מכור לי בני מעיה של פרה, Mchor li bnei me'eha shel
parah, sell me the, you know, the organs, the inner organs of
this cow, okay? This was somebody that
liked what's—what's that dish? They have sweetbreads and all those other fancy
disgusting things made from the organs. So he said, 'Sell me the
organs of the cow.' Now the organs of the cow have the
קיבה, keivah, have this stomach that normally is a gift to a
כהן. kohen. And he paid a flat price, a hundred dollars for
all of the cow organs. So here's the question. והיה בהם מתנות
כהונה, Vehayu bahem matnot kehunah, and the gifts to the כהן kohen
were there, the קיבה. keivah. נותן לכהן, Noten l'kohen,
so the buyer has to give that to the כהן kohen because,
you know, if he says 'organs', he should know that that includes,
you know, that includes the קיבה. keivah. Of course, they always are
there. ואינו מנכה לו מן הדמים, V'eino menakeh lo min hadamim, and
he cannot ask for a refund from the seller, because if you're
saying 'sell me the organs' and it's a flat price for all
of the organs, so you should know, buyer beware, that that includes
a stomach which you're not going to be able to keep, which
has to go to the כהנים. kohanim. Fine, okay, and therefore that
was the price, the price was for it, and you can't say,
'Oh, I was misled.'
He's not—he's not getting it at all.
Well, he's—it's being transferred to him and then he's passing it on
to the כהן. kohen. Okay, now, the goes on to say, לקח
הימנו במשקל, Lakach heimenu bemishkal, however if you bought it by weight,
you said, 'I'd like some organs,' and you weigh out three pounds,
and it happens to be that one of those—one of the things
amongst those was the קיבה, keivah, and that was a half of
a pound's worth, so he was being charged for a half a
pound, and he should—and he had no reason to expect that that
was going to be amongst the organs he was getting, he wanted
organs that he could eat.
So if it was—so if it was by weight, נותן לכהן, noten
l'kohen, he obviously still has to give it to the כהן, kohen,
ומנכה לו מן הדמים, umenakeh lo min hadamim, but there he can
ask for—for a discount, he can ask for his money back for
that amount—for the amount he wasn't able to keep. Anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says, אמאי, amai, why, once it was sold, why does
it have then be given to the כהן? kohen? ליהוי כמוזיק מתנות
כהונה או שהכלן, Leihavei k'mazik matnot kehunah o she'achalan, let it be
like the מתנות matnot of the כהונה kehunah have been destroyed, and
once they've been destroyed, you know, nobody can collect it. So here
too, once it's transferred ownership, why does it still have to be
given? And the answer here is quite obvious, and one wonders what
the question is. The גמרא Gemara says, שאני התם דאיתנהו בעינייהו, Shani
hatam d'isnehu b'eineihu, there they're still around. So the whole point was—was
that you cannot demand payment if it's been damaged, but wherever it
is, they have to be given, right? So if it's still around,
so who—whether it's in the hands of the butcher or the hands
of the buyer, but there's still a מצוה mitzvah to give it,
and it still belongs to the כהנים kohanim as a collective while
it's still around. The only question was—was that if it's not around,
can somebody file suit for damages? So it really makes you wonder
what the question is. Maybe the question was, if you remember yesterday,
the—there was an opinion that the reason you don't pay is not
because there's nobody who can file suit, but because of the פסוק
pasuk זה, zeh, only when it's around you have to give it.
So maybe if it's based on the פסוק pasuk זה, zeh, I
would have said maybe only if it's in the hands of the
person who originally slaughtered the animal, but once somebody else has it,
maybe that other person doesn't have to give it. Anyway, either way
the גמרא Gemara is saying that we're only talking—the issue is only
when it's destroyed. If it's around, even if it's not under the
original ownership, it obviously still has to be given.
But you
mentioned—the
tenth animal doesn't have to be given if it was sold.
Yes, but that's a different law. Right. And there are some times
where if something is purchased, the laws don't apply. So that is
exactly maybe what the גמרא Gemara was asking, based not on the
idea that nobody can file suit, אין לו תובעין, ein lo tov'in,
but a special הלכה halakha of זה. zeh. But in the end
it says yes, even if it's purchased, it has to go—be given
by the person who got it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this, תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. תשעה נכסי כהן,
Tisha nichsei kohen, there are nine gifts of the כהן. kohen. Now
there's a huge רש"י Rashi on this and there's a reasonably a—a
medium-sized תוספות Tosafot because there's not nine, there's like twenty-four.
And even if these are subdivided, the question is, anyway, they all
have different גרסאות girsa'ot here. רש"י Rashi has a גרסא girsa that
says not nine but fifteen. תוספות Tosafot has a גרסא girsa that
says not nine but seven. Anyway, everybody's bothered exactly how—why we're listing
some and not others. I'm not going to figure that out with
us. I'm just going to focus on the—the point of bringing this
in here. So this list happens to mention nine of the gifts
that the כהנים kohanim get. What are they? תרומה, Terumah, the תרומה
Terumah obviously, תרומת מעשר, Terumat maaser, the תרומה Terumah that they get
from the מעשר maaser that a לוי Levi gets, which is— the
tenth of the לוי Levi, *Levi*'s מעשר ma'aser, *Ma'aser*, and חלה challah,
*Challah*, the gift of the dough, right, when you're making a certain
size of dough, ראשית הגז reishis hagez.
*Reishis HaGez*, the first shearings, ומתנות *Umatanos*, the gifts of the זרוע
לחיים וקיבה zeroa lechayayim ve-keivah? *Zeroa Lechayayim Vekeiva*, of of slaughtering an
animal, והדמאי *VehaDemai*, and they even get the now
when there's דמאי *Demai*, this is obviously not biblical because דמאי *Demai*
is rabbinic, you buy grain from an עם am, הארץ *Am Ha'aretz*,
so there's you can't be certain that they've taken תרומות ומעשר *Terumos
Uma'aser*, you assume they've taken מעשר ma'aser *Ma'aser* because it's a tiny
bit, but you can't assume that they've taken תרומת מעשר trumas ma'aser,
*Terumas Ma'aser*, which is basically one percent, because the מעשר ma'aser, *Ma'aser*
is ten percent and the תרומת מעשר Ma'asar, *Terumas Ma'aser* is a
tenth of that, so therefore once you take when you take מעשר
maaser. *Ma'aser*, you give them the תרומת מעשר maaser *Terumas Ma'aser*, the
tenth of the tenth to a כהן Kohen, *Kohen* from דמאי *Demai*.
Okay, so that's really a type of תרומת מעשר maaser. *Terumas Ma'aser*,
but it's a special case so we mention it. והביכורים *Vehabikkurim*, obviously
the first fruit, וקרן וחומש *Vekeren Vechomesh*. Now קרן וחומש *Keren Vechomesh*
is a little unusual there because it's not part of these agricultural
things, and that is if somebody steals from a גר *Ger*, from
a convert, and swears and denies that they owe it, and then
the גר *Ger* dies. Who do they give the money back? The
תורה Torah *Torah* says you give back the קרן *Keren*, the principal,
and a fifth. But it says if the person has no has
no heirs, you give the principal and the fifth to a כהן
Kohen, *Kohen*, otherwise you give it to the person or to his
heirs. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says who doesn't have heirs? The
only person that doesn't have heirs is a convert. So in that
type of a case, the principal and fifth go to the כהנים
Kohanim, *Kohanim*. So these are some of the gifts of the כהנים
Kohanim, *Kohanim*. Now, why is this relevant for us? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says למאי *Lemai*, what's the point of saying that these
are the נכסי כהן Kohen, *Nichsei Kohen*? It doesn't say gifts to
the כהן Kohen *Kohen*, נכסי *Nichsei*, property. So property sounds like that
he fully owns it and if they're damaged you have to pay
him back. למאי *Lemai*, for what purpose is it calling it his
property? לאו להוציא בדיינים *Lav Lehotzi'ah Bedayanim*, doesn't it mean you'd have
to pay him back? Now obviously it means you can't say well
yeah after I've given it to him if I damage it I
would pay him back because then that would also be patently obvious.
So by emphasizing they're owned by the כהן Kohen? *Kohen*, doesn't isn't
it suggesting even before you've given it to him he really fully
owns it and if you damage you have to compensate? So isn't
that what's being suggested? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא *Lo*,
no, that's not the point. לכדתנן *Lichiditnan*, it's telling you another point
like we taught in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* in ביכורים *Bikkurim*. למה
אמרו נכסי כהן Kohen *Lama Amru Nichsei Kohen*, what is the point
of saying that they are owned by the כהן Kohen *Kohen*? שקונה
בהן עבדים וקרקעות ובהמה טמאה *Shekoneh Bahen Avadim Vekarka'os Uveheimah Temei'ah*, to
tell you that there is no restrictions what he can use the
money for. Right, there are some things that you have serious restrictions
about how to use, like you wouldn't say the meat of a
חטאת *Chatas* is נכסי כהן Kohen *Nichsei Kohen*. He can't eat it
out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*, he can't use
it to buy other things with. These types of things, even though
תרומה Terumah *Terumah* has קדושה kedusha, *Kedushah* and can't be eaten by
non-כהנים kohanim *Kohanim*, James here has a nice business going in being
a you know a whatever you know a a תרומה Teruma *Terumah*
dealer, exactly, because he knows there are plenty of כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim*
that are trying to get rid of their תרומה truma, *Terumah*, he
knows a group of כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim* that you know that are
are dying to buy anything even תרומה truma *Terumah* if they can
get it at a good price. Okay, so I'm going to give
my תרומה truma *Terumah* to James and he's going to give me
for that you know a pig or a slave, it doesn't matter
what I get with it, although it has to be eaten properly,
I'm allowed to use it to buy and do with it whatever
I want as long as when eventually it's consumed it's consumed properly.
So that's the emphasis of saying they are the property of a
כהן Kohen. *Kohen*, that he has complete freedom how to use that
money you know how to how to how to spend that money.
Okay, when you actually eat it there are limits by some of
it like the תרומה truma *Terumah*, not by others, right, זרוע לחיים
וקיבה zeroa lechayayim ve-keivah. *Zeroa Lechayayim Vekeiva* has no קדושה kedusha *Kedushah*,
but to spend it you have full freedom. שקונה בהן עבדים וקרקעות
*Shekoneh Bahen Avadim Vekarka'os*, slaves, land, בהמה טמאה *Beheimah Temei'ah*, even non-kosher
animals you can buy with your תרומה *Terumah*, ובעל חוב נוטלם בחובו
*Uva'al Chov Notlam Bechovo*, you can pay off debts with it, ואשה
בכתובתה *Ve'ishah Biksivasah*, if you're you know a woman could collect her
כתובה *Kesuvah* from this from this stuff if her husband the כהן
kohen *Kohen* died or divorced her, וספר תורה Torah *Vesefer Torah*, and
you can buy a ספר תורה Torah *Sefer Torah* with it. Now
רש״י *Rashi* says I don't know what that word is doing there
because if you can buy a pig with it of course you
can buy a ספר תורה *Sefer Torah* with it. So רש״י *Rashi*
doesn't know why that was added to the list. But okay, anyway,
anyway that is the end of that so you can't prove it
from that phrase, that doesn't mean that's just to speak about the
כהן kohen *Kohen*'s freedom of use, that does not mean that if
you damaged it before the כהן kohen, *Kohen* got it you would
have to compensate.
Now, ההוא ליווא *Hahu Liva'ah*, there was a לוי Levi *Levi*, דהוה
חטיף מתנתיה *Dehava Chatif Matnaso*. Now we're sort of shifting gears a
little bit from this ממון שאין לו תובעים *Mamon She'ein Lo Tove'im*.
There was a לוי Levi *Levi* that grabbed the מתנות *Matanos*. He
was hovering around the butcher and as soon as the animal was
שחט shecht *Shechted* he ran in and he grabbed the זרוע לחיים
וקיבה zeroa lechayayim ve-keivah *Zeroa Lechayayim Vekeiva*. Now there's a little problem,
he's a לוי Levi, *Levi* and it says you give it to
a כהן kohen, *Kohen*. Okay, so let's take a look. אתו אמרו
ליה לרב *Atu Amru Lei LeRav*, so people came and told רב
Rav *Rav* what this לוי Levi, *Levi* was doing. אמר להו *Amar
Lehu* he said to them, לא מסתייא דלא שקלינן מיניה *Lo Mistaya
Delo Shaklina Minei*, what, it's not enough for this guy, מסתייא *Mistaya*
is an interesting phrase meaning like it's not enough, but לא מסתייא
*Lo Mistaya* is usually like the idiomatic phrase, it's not enough for
you דלא שקלינן מיניה *Delo Shaklina Minei* that we don't take take
his own זרוע לחיים וקיבה zeroa lechayayim ve-keivah. *Zeroa Lechayayim Vekeiva* away
from him when he slaughters his own animals, we don't take them
from him and demand that he give it to a כהן. kohen
So that wasn't enough, that he was able to keep his own,
אלא מחטף נמי חטיף, ella miktaf nami khatif, you have to go
grab other people's? So how could we allow that? So the גמרא
Gemara now wants to understand what this what רב Rav, meant by
all of this. ורב, Ve-Rav, so but רב, Rav אי אקרו עם,
ei ikru am, if לויים Levi'im are called an עם, am? a
nation, משקל נמי לשקלו, mishkal nami lishklo, why didn't he take from
them, מנייהו? minaihu? And אי לא אקרו עם, ei lo ikru am,
if they're not called a nation, רחמנא פטרינהו, Rachmana patreinhu, the תורה
exempted them. What does that mean? Because the תורה says who gives
the זרוע לחיים וקיבה? zero'a lechayayim vekeivah, It says, and this is
what you shall take, מאת זבחי הזבח אם שור אם שה. me-et
zivchei ha-zevach im shor im seh.
No, no, but wait, what's the פסוק pasuk by עם? am It
says, yeah, oh,
מאת העם. me-et ha-am.
This is what you shall take מאת העם me-et ha-am from the
people, מאת זבחי הזבח אם שור אם שה. me-et zivchei ha-zevach im
shor im seh. So does the sense of עם am exclude לויים?
Levi'im? Because we know from many ways the לויים Levi'im are not
part of the standard nation in terms of getting an inheritance and
going out to war. So does the phrase מאת העם me-et ha-am
include the לויים Levi'im or not? Which is a fascinating question. I
mean, does it apply to narratives? When the תורה says like ויהי
העם כמתאננים? vayehi ha-am kemitonanim?
Maybe that maybe what's a little bit what informed, you know, this
question because often עם am in the narratives are when the people
are acting, you know, in a troublesome way. So anyway, this is
a question, does עם am include לויים? Levi'im? So there's a possibility
that although the gifts are given only to כהנים, kohanim the only
the לויים Levi'im are not obligated to give them. Only the non-לוי,
Levi only the general ישראל Yisrael gives it. So the לויים Levi'im
aren't entitled to receive them, but they're not obligated to give them.
And that could be what רב Rav was saying. רב Rav would
say, it's not enough for him that he doesn't have to give
it, but he's actually going and grabbing somebody else's? Okay, but now
the גמרא Gemara says, but one minute, if you held that as
a לוי Levi he has to give, why are you letting him
get away with not giving? And if you held that as a
לוי Levi he's not called עם am and he doesn't have to
give, so why did you say, oh, it's not enough that he
doesn't give? There's a reason he doesn't give. He's entitled not to
give because he's excluded. So what why was רב Rav implying that
he should be giving but he doesn't? If he should be giving,
let's force him to give, and if he doesn't, if he's entitled
not to, why are you making a big deal about it? So
the גמרא Gemara says,
so the גמרא Gemara says,
מספקא ליה. mesafeka leh. רב Rav has a doubt, אי אקרו עם
אי לא אקרו עם, ei ikru am ei lo ikru am, whether
they are obligated or not. So רב Rav says is look, this
לוי, Levi it might be he's obligated, but because we're not sure,
we let him get away with not giving זרוע לחיים וקיבה. zero'a
lechayayim vekeivah? And that's not enough for him. It's not enough that
out of our doubt he doesn't have to give, he even goes
ahead and grabs somebody else's. And that רב Rav was very offended
by, right, you know, חוצפה chutzpah this guy. Yes. Okay.
What about ספק דאורייתא לחומרא? safek de-oraita le-chumra?
So that's a good question, but this gets to a principle and
it's also going to be about how we deal with why we,
you know, don't give these gifts, is because this is
a ממונות mamonot matter, which is does, you know, who owns this?
Because this has no קדושה, kedusha, it's a question of who owns
it. And by ממונות mamonot issues we say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה.
ha-motzi me-chavero alav ha-re'ayah. If you want me to give pay you,
you say I owe you money, you have the burden of proof.
Now it is true that, you know, sometimes the question is raised,
why do we look at something through that lens, through the civil
lens, if you would the חושן משפט Choshen Mishpat lens and not
the like, you know, יורה דעה Yoreh De'ah lens? Meaning why don't
we say, I say to you, hey, if you think that this
hundred dollars is yours, prove it. You have the burden of proof.
Nobody knows if you deserve זרוע לחיים וקיבה zroa lechayayim vekeiva or
not. I'm a לוי, Levi if you want to prove it. But
why don't we say, okay, but look at it through the other
lens, maybe I have a מצוה, mitzvah, ספק דאורייתא לחומרא. safek de-oraita
le-chumra. But if that's true, this is a classic question that the
ברכת שמואל Birchat Shmuel asks, who's like a student of רב חיים
Rav Chaim from, of רב חיים בריסקר. Rav Chaim Brisker. He says,
say it by all cases of monetary issues. I don't know if
I owe you a hundred dollars or not. You have the burden
of proof. Why don't I say, I might be stealing your money,
ספק גזל ספק גזל לחומרא, safek gezel safek gezel le-chumra, I should
have to give you the money. And so the answer is that
when something intersects those areas, but the base but the basic question
is do I owe you and it's civil, we determine the civil
issue and there and the other questions about is it גזל, gezel,
do I have a מצוה mitzvah to give it, etc., are defined
in terms based on how we would adjudicate it as a civil
issue. You know, it's sort of like, it's sort of like a
what do you call it? Like a jurisdiction question. Exactly, jurisdiction, but
which category of the law you put it in and you primarily
put it in that category and that defines, you know, your the
scope of your obligation. Okay, so that's basically the point. Because it's
monetary and we don't know, we're not going to demand it. And
therefore רב Rav would say, and that wasn't enough, he had to
go grab it. So now we're going to actually have this interesting
question about whether לויים Levi'im have to give זרוע לחיים וקיבה. zroa
lechayayim vekeiva Are they included in עם am, or not? So let's
take a look.
I was just wondering why couldn't he just be saying it's not
enough that he doesn't have to give?
I know, you could have read it that way. Like some people
aren't happy with what they've got. He gets out of doing it
and right. Yeah, I it's true, but that's the way the גמרא
Gemara somehow understands... that he was felt that there was something wrong
or problematic with the very fact that he wasn't giving, yeah, exactly,
that he was able to keep it, or questionable about it. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara. says like this.
יתיב רב פפא, Yosiv Rav Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa was
sitting וקאמר לה להא שמעתא, ve-kamar lah hai shma'ta, and he was
telling over this discussion and about how רב Rav's felt that it
was doubtful if a לוי Levi, has to give. אתא רב אידי
בר אבין לרב פפא, Ata Rav Idi bar Abin le-Rav Pappa, so
רב אידי בר אבין Rav Idi bar Abin asked רב פפא Rav
Pappa to try to prove it one way or the other. ארבע
מתנות עניים שבכרם, Arba matnot aniyim she-be-kerem, okay, there are four, here's
a nice little summary of, we had a little before about a
little list of the gifts of כהנים, kohanim. here's a little summary
of the gifts that go to the עניים aniyim during the time
of harvest, whether it's in the vineyard or the trees or the
or the grain, the field. So let's take a look. There are
four gifts you give the עניים aniyim in the vineyard: הפרט והעוללות.
ha-peret ve-ha-olelot. פרט Peret is basically the droppings that's like לקט leket
by the grain. עוללות Olelot is types of
unwell-developed clusters. Okay, not unripe, but clusters normally have, you know, they're
like a triangle, so they have what's the edges of that of
the top of the triangle are called the shoulder, the כתף, katef,
and then there's the point at the bottom which is the נטף,
nataf, the dripping part. So if somehow the cluster's formed in a
way that it doesn't have the shoulder part or the dripping part
at the bottom, so it's not just unripe. Unripe means it hasn't
finished developing. This is like a one that's not developing normally. Okay,
so that you leave for the עניים. aniyim. That's עוללות. olelot.
והשכחה והפאה, ve-ha-shikcha ve-ha-pe'ah, and the classic ones of if you forgot
to harvest some of the some of the clusters and you intentionally
leave over a corner. That's in the vineyard. ושלש שבתבואה, Ve-shalosh she-be-tvu'ah,
three by grain: הלקט, ha-leket, which is things you dropped when you
were harvesting, השכחה, ha-shikcha, things you forgot about, והפאה, ve-ha-pe'ah, and the
corner. שנים שבאילן, Shnayim she-be-ilan, two in a tree: השכחה והפאה. ha-shikcha
ve-ha-pe'ah. There's no droppings, but there is you things that you forgot
to to harvest and you leave intentionally a part of the tree,
literally a corner, but it means you leave a section. So
כולן, kulan, so of all of these gifts to the poor, אין
בהן טובת הנאה לבעלים. ein bahen tovat hana'ah le-be'alim. The owners do
not have a right to determine who gets it. And the גמרא's
Gemara going to say because the verse says תעזוב אותם, ta'azov otam,
right? And if you think about the images, although one could wonder
about the whole story with רות Ruth where בועז Boaz gets a
little involved, but anyway, but if you think about the classic images,
it's basically that the owner isn't there and the poor are there
and they're just and they are collecting and they're harvesting. You leave
it for the poor. You do not give it to the poor,
you leave it for the poor, so you don't get to say
I only want to give it to this guy and not to
somebody else. Okay, so that there's no טובת הנאה. tovat hana'ah. ואפילו
עני שבישראל מוציא מידו, Ve-afilu ani she-be-Yisrael motzi mi-yado, if you're a
poor person but you happen to have a little one tree to
your name or a little piece of a vineyard, you also have
to leave it to the poor. You cannot say hey I'm poor
I'll just take it myself. We're going to learn from a פסוק
pasuk that you have to leave it for other poor, even if
you happen to be poor yourself. Okay, that is by those gifts
to the poor. Now, מעשר עני המתחלק בתוך ביתו, ma'aser ani ha-mitchalek
be-toch beito, let's say you have however not these gifts to the
poor but the מעשר, maaser the tenth, which is every third and
sixth year, the second מעשר maaser of your grain that you separate
off to give to the poor. If it's and it's divided in
your house, יש בו טובת הנאה לבעלים. yesh bo tovat hana'ah le-be'alim.
There and we'll see in the the גמרא Gemara because it says
the word כי תתן, ki titein, you give it to the poor,
so you get to decide which poor person you give it to.
Okay, that and again the same with the same principle is true,
even if the person happens to be poor who's giving it, he
has an obligation to give it to another poor person. We'll learn
that from a verse. תוספות Tosafot interestingly says based on a ירושלמי
Yerushalmi and other things, he emphasizes the phrase מתחלק בתוך ביתו. mitchalek
be-toch beito. And תוספות Tosafot actually says that there are two types
of מעשר עני. ma'aser ani. If you are actually separate it out
in the threshing floor, then it actually has the status of like
these other gifts to the poor, that you just leave it for
them and they come and they take it. But if you've brought
it into your house and you separate it, then you get a
greater sort of sense of possession and ownership and then you give
it rather than leave it and you get to decide who it
goes to. Okay, so it's interesting that there's I was fascinated the
idea, it doesn't say. It doesn't say there's nothing wrong with doing
it in your house if that's your question. But it's fascinating the
idea that there could be two different statuses about how you give
it to the poor based on where you are separating it off
from. תוספות Tosafot also says by the way another interesting point, that
just because you have the right to give it to somebody, if
let's say again like some of the scenarios we talked about before,
a poor person comes in and grabs it, you would not be
able to take it back from him. Okay, yes, he he subverted
your your sort of, you know, little entitlement, your you know, your
ability to to choose, but at the end of the day, if
he actually grabbed it, he actually would be able to take possession
of it. Okay, anyway, that is מעשר, maaser that is מעשר עני.
ma'aser ani. Now, ושאר מתנות כהונה, ve-sha'ar matnot kehunah, it's a funny
phrase. the other gifts of the כהן, kohen what do you mean
the other? We didn't talk about any. But okay, gifts as opposed
to the gifts of the poor. But okay, the gifts to the
כהן, kohen. כגון, kegon, maybe שאר she'ar here means as opposed to
something like תרומה and the classic gifts, okay? But the other gifts
to the כהן, kohen for example, זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zroa lechayayim vekeiva.
okay, the arm and you know, whatever, the maw and the stomach,
אין מוציאין אותן מידו, ein motzi'in otan miyado, you do not force
a כהן kohen to give it, okay?
This is contrasting, right? Because an עני ani has to give to
another עני ani these gifts to the poor. How about a כהן?
kohen, Does he have to give to another כהן kohen the זרוע
לחיים וקיבה? zroa lechayayim vekeiva. So it says no, you do not
force a כהן kohen to give it.
לא מכהן לכהן ולא מלוי ללוי. lo mikohen lekohen velo milevi lelevi.
Not from one כהן kohen to another and not from a לוי
Levi to another. Now that's a little bizarre because a לוי Levi
is never entitled to receive it. Right. So what does that even
mean? Okay, so anyway, we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara
ארבע מתנות שבכרם. arba matnot shebakarem. Okay, now that's the end of
the ברייתא. braita. Now we're going to first analyze it, but in
the end our focus is going to be on that last line
and through the lens of is a לוי levi obligated to give?
Because it sounds like you don't make a לוי levi give it
to another לוי, levi but you would make a לוי levi give
it to a כהן. kohen. So this in the end is brought
to bear on the question of is a לוי levi obligated to
give? But let's first analyze it piece by piece.
לא מכהן לכהן ולא מלוי ללוי. lo mikohen lekohen velo milevi lelevi.
I'm sorry, so ארבע מתנות שבכרם. arba matnot shebakarem. So now we're
taking it apart piece by piece. Four gifts of the vineyard: הפרט
ועוללות השכחה והפאה. haperet ve'olelot hashichchah vehape'ah. So where do you get
them from? דכתיב, dechativ, the verse says, וכרמך לא תעולל, vecharmacha lo
te'olel, do not be עולל olel your vineyard. So we understand that
עולל olel means picking up even the droppings, so that's the idea
of עוללות. olelot. ופרט כרמך לא תלקט, uferet carmecha lo telaket, and
do not gather harvest the פרט peret of your vineyard. So that
is understood to mean the פרט peret is, I'm sorry, I mis-said
it. The עולל olel is the ones that are not developed, okay?
So do not remove the undeveloped things. And the פרט, peret, the
droppings of your כרם, kerem, do not gather. So that's the פרט
peret and the עוללות, olelot, the droppings and the undeveloped clusters. וכתיב,
vechativ, so that's two. כי תבצור כרמך לא תעולל אחריך. ki tivtzor
carmecha lo te'olel acharecha. So it seems to be the same thing.
When you harvest your vineyard, do not be עולל olel afterwards, which
עולל olel before meant these undeveloped clusters. But here, אמר רב לוי,
amar Rav Levi, אחריך, acharecha, the word אחריך acharecha זו שכחה, zu
shichchah, means forgetting. Because the whole point of forgetting is that you've
left it behind. Okay, actually there's a משנה Mishna. that says that
if I had more, let's say, rows of grain to harvest and
I forgot what I had yet to harvest, that's not שכחה. shichchah.
שכחה shichchah is not I forgot that I still have to finish
harvesting. That's not like I left it behind. שכחה shichchah is only
stuff that I harvested already and I forgot to pick up. Okay,
stuff that's behind me. So the word אחריך acharecha refers to שכחה,
shichchah, stuff that is behind you that you forgot about. פאה, pe'ah,
how do you know you give פאה pe'ah by the vineyard? גמר
אחריך אחריך מזית. gamar acharecha acharecha mizzayit. You learn a גזירה שוה
gezeirah shavah by the אחריך acharecha by the olives. What does it
say by the olives? דכתיב כי תחבוט זיתך לא תפאר אחריך. dechativ
ki tachbot zeitecha lo tefa'er acharecha. When you sort of, you know,
harvest your olive tree, do not be תפאר tefa'er the glory afterwards.
So afterwards means שכחה, shichchah, and now we're going to learn from
the word תפאר tefa'er that it means פאה. pe'ah. ותנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל, vetana devei Rabbi Yishmael, שלא תטול תפארתו ממנו, shelo tital tifarto
mimenu, do not remove its beauty. It's interesting in Hebrew that sometimes
certain, I think it's in English too some of these cases, sometimes
verbs of words can mean to do something, sometimes it can mean
to undo something. So for example,
להשרש אחריו lehashresh acharav from the word שורש shoresh does not mean
to plant roots, it means to uproot. Okay, so I think you
have that in English, right? To shell walnuts means to remove their
shells. Okay, so it's actually funny if you look at some nuts,
it says shelled and salted. Of course, shelled means the shells were
removed, unshelled.
Salted means that the salt was added on. Anyway, so תפאר tefa'er
is meant to remove the פאה, pe'ah, remove the glory. How do
you remove the glory of something? You take all the stuff away.
So don't remove the glory means leave a little bit behind. Okay,
so by the olive it says לא תפאר אחריך. lo tefa'er acharecha.
So לא תפאר lo tefa'er is פאה, pe'ah, אחריך acharecha is שכחה.
shichchah. Since we have that by the olive tree, we make a
גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah to the vine and we say there's this
idea of פאה pe'ah by the vine as well.
Okay, פרט ושכחה. peret veshichchah. What? What's between פרט peret and שכחה?
shichchah?
פרט peret is just the word for, no, פרט peret is droppings.
The difference between לקט, leket, which פרט peret is a type of
לקט. leket. The difference between לקט leket and שכחה shichchah is לקט
leket is I see it fall from my hand. I haven't forgotten
it, it just some dropped out of my hand. Don't pick it
up. שכחה shichchah is there was a sheaf back there that I
was planning on going back and bringing into the house and I
forgot about it. Okay, that's שכחה. shichchah.
Okay, now שלש שבתבואה, shalosh shebatvu'ah, three by the grain: הלקט והשכחה
והפאה. haleket vehashichchah vehape'ah. So לקט leket is again the droppings that
you know that it dropped, שכחה shichchah is you forgot about it
behind you, and פאה pe'ah is an intentional leaving off of a
corner. דכתיב, dechativ, the verse says, ובקוצרכם את קציר ארצכם, uvkutzrechem et
ketzir artzechem, when you harvest your harvesting of your field, לא תכלה
פאת שדך בקוצרך, lo techaleh pe'at sadecha bekutzrecha, do not finish the
corner of your field in your harvesting. do not destroy the corner
of the field. Okay, that's the פאה. Pe'ah. ולקט קצירך לא תלקט
V'leket k'tzircha lo telaket and do not gather up the droppings, and
how do you know and how do you know so that's לקט
Leket and שכחה Shich'chah and how do you and פאה Pe'ah and
how do you know שכחה? Shich'chah? כי תקצור קצירך בשדך Ki tiktzor
k'tzircha b'sadecha when you harvest ושכחת עומר בשדה V'shachachta omer basadeh you
forgot about a sheaf, sheaf or sheaf? Sheaf. Sheaf. What? Sheaf. Sheaf.
Sheaf. Sheaf is what you put like a knife in, right? Okay,
a sheath. Right. You forgot a sheaf.
Sheaf with a th?
No, with an f.
F. F. A sheath is what no sheath is what you put
like your your scabbard your dagger in.
Yeah, yeah, right.
But this is a
sheaf, sheaf with a sh.
Yeah, yeah, okay, right.
Okay. ושכחת עומר בשדה V'shachachta omer basadeh you forget a sheaf. Anyway,
so that's where you get the three by the grain. Very those
are the most explicit. שניים שבאילן Shnayim she'be'ilan how do you know
two of the tree? No droppings, no only the issue of שכחה
ופאה. Shich'chah u'pe'ah. שכחה ופאה Shich'chah u'pe'ah דכתיב De'chtiv this is what
we just said. כי תחבוט זיתך לא תפאר אחריך Ki tachbot zeitecha
lo tefa'er acharecha so אחריך Acharecha we already said means stuff you
left behind you, stuff you forgot about and לא תפאר Lo tefa'er
do not remove its glory means don't totally strip it bare, leave
over some, leave פאה. Pe'ah. ותנא דבי רבי ישמעאל V'tana d'vei Rabbi
Yishmael שלא תטול תפארתו ממנו She'lo tital tifarto mimenu do not strip
it of all its glory, leave over section that's פאה. Pe'ah. אחריך
Acharecha and behind you as we said זו שכחה. Zu Shich'chah. Fine,
that's very nice, we see from all the פסוקים Psukim all the
different gifts to the poor on those in those different scenarios. Now,
going back to the next line of this of this וכולן אין
בהם טובת הנאה לבעלים V'chulan ein bahem tovat hana'ah l'ba'alim none of
them do the owners have the right to decide who gets it.
מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama what's the reason? עזיבה כתיבא בהו Azivah ktiva
behu it says you should abandon it to the poor, you leave
the picture, you let them come and take, you do not give
it to them. Okay, so that is by these gifts. ואפילו עני
שבישראל מוציאין אותו מידו V'afilu ani she'be'Yisrael motzi'in oto miyado even a
poor person you would force him you'd take it out of his
hands you'd force him to give leave it to the other poor.
דכתיב De'chtiv ולקט קצירך לא תלקט לעני V'leket k'tzircha lo telaket l'ani
ולגר תעזוב אותם you should leave them for the poor and for
the sojourner להזהיר עני על שלו L'hazhir ani al shelo to say
even the עני Ani has to leave it. Where do you get
from the פסוק? Pasuk? So the way the גמרא Gemara reads it
is ולקט קצירך לא תלקט V'leket k'tzircha lo telaket לעני L'ani. that
that the עני Ani should not be תלקט לקט קצירך. Telaket leket
k'tzircha. Okay, I'm talking to you, the עני, Ani, לעני. Okay, that's
how it reads it. Anyway, so even the poor leaves it for
the other poor. Now ומעשר עני U'ma'asar ani that's about those. How
about the מעשר, maaser the tithe to the poor, which is every
third and sixth year? המתחלק בתוך הבית Hamitchalek b'toch habayit if it's
done in the house יש בו טובת הנאה לבעלים Yesh bo tovat
hana'ah l'ba'alim there the owners do get to decide who gets to
get it. ומאי טעמא U'mai ta'ama why? נתינה כתיבא ביה Netinah ktiva
bei it says you shall give to the poor, so that means
you get to decide, you get to control which poor you're giving
it to. ואפילו עני שבישראל מוציאין אותו מידו V'afilu ani she'be'Yisrael motzi'in
oto miyado even if a poor person has some grain in a
little field he has to give מעשר מעשר עני. Ma'asar ma'asar ani.
Why? דאמר רבי אלעזר D'amar Rabbi Elazar
גמר לגר לגר מהתם Gmar lager lager me'hatam makes a גזירה שוה
Gezeirah shavah in both it says leave it to the עני Ani
and to the sojourner מה להלן מוזהר עני על שלו Mah lehalan
muzhar ani al shelo the same way by the normal by the
droppings in the field and that stuff an עני Ani has to
give it even for another עני Ani אף כאן Af kan even
for מעשר שני Ma'asar sheni מוזהר עני על שלו Muzhar ani al
shelo he has to give it now to others. Now you might
think by the way that the principle here is it actually does
lead to interesting questions because on the one hand we say that
even if somebody is very poor, you know, he should be giving
צדקה, Tzedakah, which actually is an you know on the one hand
seems like unfair but on the other hand it really is very
powerful because it first of all it brings home the message that
no matter how disadvantaged you are there are people that are more
disadvantaged than you and by the way you're not so disadvantaged you
have enough that you're having you have at least a little piece
of a field that you're having the opportunity to give לקט שכחה
ופאה Leket Shich'chah u'Pe'ah and מעשר עני Ma'asar ani and it also
and this was really I have to you know say that this
was a very powerful lesson that I learned on my at my
on my wedding day or the whatever day after whatever from my
wife's grandfather עליו השלום Alav hashalom who was Leo Heck he was
like a big very important in the Jewish community in terms of
you know raising money for Jewish causes and doing a lot of
important things anyway we had somebody come to the wedding who had
like ממש Mamash you know no money and they gave us a
and she and she gave a gift and it was like a
plastic kitchen set you know like a ladle and a stirrer maybe
cost like five dollars at a dollar store and I said like
you know why did she have to do this like you know
she needs this money much more than I did why we don't
really you know need this like you know I would have been
totally happy for her just to come and you know so my
grandfather said it means you know it it means a lot to
her that she's able to give you a gift you know that
that she is a you know she's a functioning member of society
you know and she's a participating member of society it means so
much more to her that she's able to give it you know
than you know she no people don't want to be נעבעך Nebech
right people want to be able so there's something very powerful about
saying to even the poor who are always receiving that you actually
have the when you have the opportunity or whatever you actually have.
also are equal members of society you also contribute and give and
so on. So there's something sort of very powerful about that. That
being said, for example, when you are giving like if people give
מעשר כספים, maaser kesafim, they're entitled to if they themselves are poor
they're entitled to use a lot of the מעשר כספים maaser kesafim
for for their own needs. So that's an interesting question. When does
it go outside the house and when do you sort of give
it but you can actually use it because you yourself charity starts
at home, which is also a principle. So anyway those I think
are very important ideas around this issue about the עני ani giving.
Now but now we continue.
He says okay where were we? Okay
so now back to the reason we quoted all of that. ושאר
מתנות כהונה כגון זרוע לחיים וקיבה אין מוציאין אותן לא מכהן לכהן,
V'shaar matnot kehuna kegon zroa lechayayim vekeiva ein motzi'in otan lo mikohen
l'kohen, but when you're dealing with the gifts of the כהונה, kehuna,
then it's not like the poor. You don't make a poor you
make him give to other poor but here you don't make a
כהן kohen give to other כהן kohen? the זרוע לחיים וקיבה zroa
lechayayim vekeiva he can keep it. ולא מלוי ללוי, V'lo milevi l'levi,
which is a bizarre statement because לויים leviyim are not entitled to
it. But the גמרא Gemara is interested in the implication. הא מלוי
לכהן, Ha milevi l'kohen, but if to if a לוי levi was
refusing to give it to a כהן, kohen if a לוי levi
is refusing to give it to a לוי levi. why are we
going to get involved? The other לוי levi isn't entitled to it.
But if a לוי levi. is refusing to give it to a
כהן, kohen. מוציאין, motzi'in, it implies that you force him to give
it. אלמא איקרו עם, Alma ikru am, you see that they're called
a עם, am they're in the category of עם am, and they
have to give these gifts. So the גמרא Gemara says a very
strange read of this משנה. No, when it says like the זרוע
ולחיים וקיבה zroa ulechayayim vekeiva it means like the זרוע לחיים וקיבה
zroa l'chayayim v'keiva but not the זרוע לחיים וקיבה. zroa l'chayayim v'keiva
כגון הזרוע ולא זרוע. Kegon hazroa velo zroa. If it's something like
the זרוע zroa you wouldn't you would for that you would force
a לוי levi to give to a כהן kohen. but we're not
talking about literally the זרוע. zroa. ומאי ניהו, Umai nihu, what's this
thing that's like a זרוע? zroa? מעשר ראשון. Maaser rishon. It's מעשר.
ma'aser Now why is מעשר ma'aser like a זרוע? zroa? Only because
maybe it is not it's a gift that is not sanctified. You
know it doesn't have קדושה kedusha, to it like the זרוע לחיים
וקיבה. zroa l'chayayim v'keiva. So now we've totally reread the case. It's
not זרוע לחיים וקיבה zroa l'chayayim v'keiva it's מעשר ראשון. maaser rishon.
So now it's saying if you have מעשר ראשון maaser rishon which
goes to a לוי levi. normally, you don't force a כהן kohen
to give it to another כהן. kohen If a כהן kohen wants
to keep the מעשר ראשון maaser rishon for himself, this is suggesting
he can, which is strange. He's a כהן kohen. not a לוי.
levi. You don't force a לוי levi to give it to another
לוי. levi Okay, he's entitled to keep it to himself obviously if
or not obviously but if he's separating his own מעשר. But the
implication being you would make a לוי levi give it to a
כהן, kohen which is all very bizarre. Isn't it something that the
לויים leviyim get? So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says מעשר ראשון דלוי הוא. Maaser rishon delevi hu. What's going on
here? כהן כהן לוי Kohen kohen levi it belongs to the לויים.
leviyim. כרבי אלעזר בן עזריה, K'Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya, like Rabbi Elazar
ben Azarya. דתניא, Detanya, we learned in the ברייתא. Braitah. תרומה לכהן
מעשר ראשון ללוי, Teruma l'kohen maaser rishon l'levi, which is pretty obvious.
תרומה goes to a כהן kohen מעשר ראשון maaser rishon goes to
a לוי. levi דברי רבי עקיבא. Divrei Rabbi Akiva. רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya omer, I disagree. אף
לכהן. Af l'kohen. No, you can even give the מעשר ראשון maaser
rishon to a כהן Kohen. because כהנים Kohanim, are also in the
category of לוי. levi So so the גמרא Gemara. says one minute.
אימא דאמר רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אף לכהן, Eima d'amar Rabbi Elazar
ben Azarya af l'kohen, you could. לכהן ולא ללוי מי אמר, L'kohen
velo l'levi mi amar, he would never say a כהן Kohen has
preference because again we're trying to read this ברייתא Braitah that a
לוי levi you would force a לוי levi to give it to
a כהן. Kohen, And the it we're now saying is מעשר ראשון.
maaser rishon. So how would it be that you would prefer a
כהן Kohen, over לוי levi. and you'd force a לוי levi to
give it to a כהן? Kohen. So גמרא Gemara says אין, In,
yes. לבתר דקנסינהו עזרא, Lebatar de'kansinhu Ezra, after Ezra fined them. The
לויים leviyim basically did not make עליה aliyah during the עליה שניה
aliyah shniya in the time of Ezra. And Ezra was very upset
at them. And it's not explicit in the פסוקים psukim it's clear
that he was angry at them. But anyway the גמרא Gemara understands
that he basically said to punish them don't give them your מעשר
anymore. Just give the מעשר to the כהנים. Kohanim They're also לויים.
leviyim. So give your מעשר just to the כהנים. Kohanim So post
Ezra's תקנה takana we're saying we wouldn't force a כהן Kohen, to
give it to כהנים Kohanim, can keep it. They can keep their
own. And we would maybe even have make a force a לוי
levi to give it to a כהן. Kohen. But that's going too
far for the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says one minute.
אימר דקנסינהו עזרא, Eimar de'kansinhu Ezra, when did Ezra fine them? דלא
יהבינן להו. D'la yahavinan lehu. We don't give it to the לויים.
leviyim. We give it to the כהנים. But משקל מינייהו מי אמר,
Mishkal mineihu mi amar, he would never say you take מעשר out
of the hands of a לוי levi and give it to a
כהן. Kohen, So again this ברייתא Braitah says you don't force this
gift to go from כהן Kohen to כהן Kohen. or לוי levi...
to לוי. Levi A כהן Kohen. is entitled to keep it to
himself. A לוי Levi, is entitled to keep it to himself. But
what you do implicitly do is force a לוי Levi to give
it to a כהן. Kohen, So what are we talking about? You
can't say we're talking about מעשר ראשון maaser rishon because even if
we normally give it to a כהן Kohen after this after Ezra
we would never force a לוי Levi to give his own מעשר
ראשון maaser rishon that he separated out of his own grain we
would never force him force him to give it to a כהן
Kohen to take it out of his hands. אלא, Ela, so גמרא
Gemara says alright let's try it this way. כגון זרוע, Kegon zroa,
something like the זרוע zroa ולא זרוע velo zroa but not the
זרוע. zroa. ומאי ניהו ראשית הגז, Umai nihu reshit hagez, the first
shearings. Okay so the first shearings it doesn't say עם, am, the
people. So the first shearings is definitely something that only a לוי...
Levi gives and gives to a כהן. Kohen. So then the way
this would read is: if a כהן Kohen sheared his sheep, he
doesn't have to give that to another כהן, Kohen. he keeps his
first shearings. If a לוי Levi sheared his sheep, we wouldn't force
him to give it to another לוי, Levi which is again sort
of like obvious because another לוי Levi. doesn't deserve it, but the
point is the implication, if a לוי Levi was refusing to give
his shearings to a כהן, Kohen we would force him to give
it to a כהן. Kohen So yes, that's true by shearings, but
we're still trying to claim that זרוע לחיים וקיבה zroa l'chayayim v'keiva
they might not have to give, לויים Leviyim might be excluded. Again,
it's a very hard read because it mentions זרוע לחיים וקיבה zroa
l'chayayim v'keiva? only for the point of saying like them but not
them. Okay, but that's what we're trying again to argue, which is
that לויים Leviyim do not have to give זרוע לחיים וקיבה. Zeroa
Lechayayim veKeivah, תשמע, Tashma, we're going to try again. זה הכלל, Zeh
haklal, this is the rule. כל דבר שהוא בקדושה, Kol davar shehu
b'kedusha, anything that has sanctity to it, such as תרומה, תרומת מעשר,
and חלה, challah things of that nature, תרומה and חלה etc., מוציאין
אותה מידם, motzin osa miyadam, you take it from their hands. So
their hands must be a לוי's Levi hands, okay, because it has
קדושה, they're not entitled to eat it. So if they didn't want
to give their תרומה to a כהן, Kohen. tough luck, you force
the תרומה out of their hands and you give it to a
כהן. Kohen, וכל דבר שאינו בקדושה, V'chol davar she'eino b'kedusha, something that
does not have sanctity but that is still a gift of a
כהן, Kohen. כגון מעשר ראשון, kegon ma'aser rishon, I'm sorry, כגון הזרוע
והלחיים והקיבה, kegon hazroa v'hal'chayayim v'hakeiva, like זרוע לחיים zroa l'chayayim וקיבה
which the כהן Kohen gets but it's not a gift, אין מוציאין
אותה מידם, ein motzin osa miyadam, you don't take it out of
their hands. So here you see, it seems very clear that this
actually is a support to the idea that they're excluded, right? Because
it says you do not make a לוי Levi. give the זרוע
zroa לחיים וקיבה to a כהן. This seems to be exactly the
support that they're exempt. So the גמרא Gemara, says: No, we could
say like we said before, it doesn't prove it. כגון זרוע ולא
זרוע, Kegon zroa v'lo zroa, something like the זרוע zroa. but not
the זרוע. מאן ניהו, Man nahu, מעשר ראשון, ma'aser rishon, ולבתר דקנסינהו
עזרא. u'l'basar d'kansinu Ezra. The scenario we described before. It's מעשר ראשון,
ma'aser rishon, it doesn't have קדושה, and it says you don't force
the לוי Levi to give it to the כהן. Why? Because although
normally we give after עזרא Ezra we would give מעשר ראשון ma'aser
rishon to a כהן, we would not force it out of the
hands of a לוי. Levi So if a לוי Levi had it,
we would not force it out of his hands. So is everybody
clear what we're doing here? We have these ברייתות braisas that say
you don't עני, ani, gifts of the עני, ani, you force an
עני ani to give to other
עניים. aniyim. כהונה Kehuna gifts, you don't force a כהן to give
to a כהן or a לוי Levi to a לוי. Levi. But
the implication is you force a לוי Levi to give to a
כהן. So what case is that scenario? Okay, isn't that זרוע לחיים
וקיבה? Doesn't it prove a כהן has to give, a לוי Levi
has to give it? No, maybe it's talking about ראשית הגז. Then
we have another ברייתא braisa that says the exact opposite: you don't
force a לוי Levi to give it to a כהן. Ah, that
proves our point that the לוי Levi is exempt. No, again, maybe
this is a case of מעשר and that while normally we give
מעשר now to כהנים, we still wouldn't force it out of the
hands of a לוי. Levi So we haven't proven our case of
the זרוע לחיים whether a לוי Levi has to give or not.
Let's try one last time and then wrap up for today. So
it says like this: תשמע, Tashma, come
and hear. השוחט לכהן ולעובד כוכבים פטור מן המתנות. Hashocheit l'Kohen u'l'oveid
kochavim patur min hamatanos. If you're שחטינג shechting for a כהן or
for a non-Jew, then you don't give the gifts. For a כהן
for obvious reasons, he keeps them himself, and for a non-Jew, non-Jew
isn't obligated and if you're שחטינג shechting for him then those gifts
don't go to a כהן. הא ללוי ולישראל חייב, Ha l'Levi u'l'Yisrael
chayav, if you're שחטינג shechting for anybody who's not a כהן, a
לוי Levi or ישראל, Yisrael, חייב, chayav, you have to give the
gifts. So you see that a לוי Levi is obligated, it only
excludes a כהן. גמרא Gemara says: לא תימא הא ללוי ולישראל חייב.
Lo teima ha l'Levi u'l'Yisrael chayav. No, don't read it for a
לוי Levi and ישראל Yisrael you're obligated. אלא אימא הא ישראל חייב.
Ela eima ha Yisrael chayav. No, for a ישראל Yisrael you would
have to give. So the גמרא says: Give me a break. אבל
ללוי מאי, פטור? Aval l'Levi mai, patur? You want to say that
for a לוי Levi if it was his cow you'd be exempt?
אי הכי ליתני השוחט ללוי ולעובד כוכבים פטור מן המתנות. I hachi
lisni hashocheit l'Levi u'l'oveid kochavim patur min hamatanos.
Then tell me that. Tell me if you שחט shecht for a
לוי Levi you're
exempt מן המתנות. min hamatanos. So if you only say if you
שחט for a כהן you're exempt, it's pretty clear that if it's
the לוי's Levi cow you still have to give. ועוד, V'od, and
we taught it explicitly. התניא, Hatanya, we taught in a ברייתא. braisa.
השוחט לכהן ולעובד כוכבים פטור מן המתנות. Hashocheit l'Kohen u'l'oveid kochavim patur
min hamatanos. ללוי ולישראל, L'Levi u'l'Yisrael, if it's a cow belonging to
a לוי Levi or ישראל, Yisrael, חייב, chayav, you have to give
it. So you see that a לוי does have to give these
gifts. תיובתא דרב, Tyufta d'Rav, that is a contradiction to רב's Rav
idea that a לוי might be exempt. אז אמר לך רב, Az
amar lach Rav, רב Rav isn't going down easy. תנאי היא, Tannai
hi, there's still a תנא tanna that says my idea. דתניא, Detanya,
we taught in the ברייתא. braisa. וכפר מקדש הקדש, V'chipper mikdash hakodesh,
this is about the atonement that is done on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur for the טומאה tuma in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash So
for the holy of the קדש, kodesh, זה לפני ולפנים, zeh lifnai
v'lifnim, טומאה tuma that occurred in the Holy of Holies. The verse
goes on, אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, the tent, זה היכל, zeh heichal,
this is the היכל heichal area where the שולחן Shulchan and the
מנורה Menorah is. מזבח, Mizbeiach, כמשמעו, kemashmao, that if somebody was טמא
tamei and worked on and did the עבודה avoda on the מזבח.
mizbeiach. יכפר, Yechapper, you will atone, אלו עזרות, elu azarot, the עזרה
azara areas. So all of the words in the verse are referring
to the sins of טומאה tuma in the בית המקדש that the
קרבן korban of יום כיפור Yom Kippur atones for. And then here's
the part that's relevant for us. It says, ועל הכהנים ועל עם
הקהל יכפר, v'al Hakohanim v'al am hakahal yechapper, for the כהנים and
for the people, עם, Am. it will atone. כהנים כמשמעו, Kohanim Kemashmao,
כהנים is atones for the כהנים, עם הקהל אלו ישראל, Am HaKahal
Eilu Yisrael, the Israelites, יכפר אלו הלוויים, Yechaper Eilu HaLeviyim, and it
will atone the next word is atones for the לויים Leviyim sin
as well for the sin of טומאה. Tumah. The point being that
the לויים Leviyim are not in the word עם. Am, They need
an extra word for the לויים. Leviyim. ותניא אידך, Vetanya Idach, another
ברייתא Baraita teaches יכפר אלו עבדים, Yechaper Eilu Avadim, no, slaves,
מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי? Mai lav beha kamiflgi? Isn't this the debate?
דמר סבר איקרו עם, Demar savar ikru Am, they're called עם, Am,
and therefore the word יכפר Yechaper is not needed for the לויים,
Leviyim, and it applies to slaves, ומר סבר לא איקרו עם, Umar
savar lo ikru Am, they're not called עם, Am. and you need
another word to include the לויים. Leviyim. So you see there are
תנאים Tanaim that debate whether לויים Leviyim are included in עם. Am,
And the last line of the גמרא, I know we're a little
over, ורב VeRav make up your mind, אי סבירא ליה כהאי תנא,
I sevira lei kehai Tana, if you hold like the תנא Tana
that says they're included in עם, Am, לימא, Leima, so rule like
him, ואי סבירא ליה כהאי תנא, Ve-i sevira lei kehai Tana, if
you rule like the תנא Tana that they're not included in עם,
Am so לימא, Leima, say like him. So the גמרא says מספקא
ליה, Mesafeka lei, he doesn't know, אי כהאי תנא אי כהאי תנא,
I kehai Tana i kehai Tana, whether we go like this one
or like that one. Okay, so in the end, while the evidence
is that a לוי is included in עם Am and a לוי
is obligated in זרוע לחיים וקיבה, we end by saying that רב
Rav, thinks that there's a possibility that he's not included in עם
and he's not so certain. So at least for רב, there's a
doubt whether a לוי would have to give the gifts, and if
there's a doubt, we're not going to force him to give the
gifts because המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechaveiro alav hara'ayah. If you
can't prove that he's obligated, he gets off. We will pick up
here tomorrow.